A Guide to the Papers of Virginius Dabney 1936-1994
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Virginius Dabney 1936-1994
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7690-am
This collection consists of ca. 5,000 items (10 Hollinger boxes, ca. 4 linear shelf feet)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift of James D. Watkinson, Library of Virginia, 800 E. Broad Street, Richmond, Va. 23219 August 12, 1999.
Biographical/Historical Information
Virginius Dabney was editor of The Richmond Times-Dispatch.
Scope and Content Information
The papers contain some family correspondence and correspondence generated by his books, friendships, and memberships in various organizations. Much is of a routine or social nature.
Frequent or notable correspondents include Thomas P. Abernethy; James Lindsay Almond, Jr.; the American Society of Newspaper Editors; Arthur Ashe, Jr.; James Henry Bailey; Gerald L. Baliles; William B. Bean; James A. Bear; Francis L. Berkeley, Jr.; Thomas J. Bliley, Jrl; Albert Sidney Britt, Jr.; Staige Blackford; Tom Boushall; and Harry F. Byrd, Jr..
Also J. Rives Childs; Thomas D. Clark; John N. Dalton; Jonathan Daniels; Colgate W. Darden, Jr.; Dr. John Staige Davis; Jeremiah A. Denton, Jr.; Alonzo Thomas Dill; Hardy Cross Dillard, Murrell Edmunds; Ernest McNeill Eller; Junius R. Fishburne, Jr.; Guy Friddell; Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr.; Mills E. Godwin, Jr.; George W. Grayson and William Hershey Greer, Jr.
Also Charles J. Harkrader; Albertis S. Harrison, Jr.; Frank L. Hereford, Jr.; Linwood Holton; William S. Howland; Jenkin Lloyd Jones; Albert S. Kemper, Jr.; James J. Kilpatrick; Arthur L. Kinsolving; John T. Kneebone; John S. Knight; Theodore Fred Kuper; Jeff MacNelly; Dumas Malone; Alf J. Mapp, Jr.; John O. Marsh, Jr.; Charles McDowell; and Harry M. Meacham.
Also William Shands Meacham, Elizabeth Copeland Norfleet; Richard D. Obenshain, William Offley; Charlton Ogburn; Robert M. O'Neil, Dr. Peter N. Pastore, Fred G. Pollard, Lewis Powell, Jr.; Sir Peter Ramsbotham; Frank G. Rankin, Jr.; Davis T. Ratcliffe; James Reston, Charles S. Robb; Joseph C. Robert; James I. Robertson, Jr.; Paul Rockwell; John C. rogers, Parke Rouse, Jr.; and Louis D. Rubin.
Also David E. Satterfield; T. J. Sellers; Edgar F. Shannon, Jr.; C. Alphonoso Smith, Charles Smith, William B. Spong, Jr.; John C. Stennis; Lewis L. Strauss; Emory M. Thomas; Thomas H. Thompson; Paul Trible; Barbara Tuchman; William M. Tuck; George H. Tucker; Edward Weeks; Sir John Wheeler-Bennett; Bell Wiley, J. Harvie Wilkinson, Jr.; Langbourne M. Williams; Robert Archer Wilson; Henry Alexander Wise, Jr.; Tom Wolfe; and Louis B. Wright.
There is also a letter from Dabney to Eudora Welty. With the Davis T. Ratcliffe letters are letters to him from Frank Harris.
Specific topics include Harry Byrd and the Byrd machine particularly in the 9th Congressional District; University of Virginia controversies including membership in Farmington Country Club and Olden Polynice; James McConnell; presidential impeachment; race relations including growing up as an African-American in Charlottesville, Va. in the 1930s; modernization in the Episcopal Church; Episcopal High School; the United States Historical Society; and his books "The Jefferson Scandals," "The Last Review," Mr. Jefferson's University," "Pistols and Pointed Pens," "Richmond," "Virginia Commonwealth University," and "Virginius Dabney's Virginia."
A few snapshots include one of the Shah of Iran in 1960.
Contents List
- Correspondence, A 1956-1992 (Box 1)
- Author's Guild 1976 Dec 8-1977 Mar 21 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, B 1956-1992, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Biographies of Virginius Dabney 1965-1990 (Box 1)
- Staige Blackford Correspondence 1975-1988 (Box 1)
- Tom Boushall Correspondence 1969-1981 (Box 1)
- Bryan Family Correspondence 1977-1981 (Box 1)
- Harry F. Byrd, Jr. Correspondence 1969-1988 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, C 1956-1992, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Correspondence, D 1956-1992, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Dabney Family Correspondence 1970-1991 (Box 2)
- Dabney Family Correspondence - Natalie Dabney Arnold 1988-1989 (Box 2)
- Dabney Family Correspondence - B. Bragg 1987-1993 (Box 2)
- Dabney Family Correspondence - Barbara Dabney 1988-1992 (Box 2)
- Dabney Family Correspondence - Lewis Dabney III 1975-1992 (Box 2)
- Dabney Family Correspondence - Pope "Buck" and Mary Dabney 1977-1992 (Box 3)
- Dabney Family Correspondence - Richard Dabney 1979-1982 (Box 3)
- Dabney Family Correspondence - Robert Dabney III 1985-1986 (Box 3)
- Dabney Family Correspondence - W. Armstrong Price 1975-1976 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, E 1956-1992 (Box 3)
- Episcopal Church (2 folders) 1967-1991 (Box 3)
- Episcopal High School 1984-1991 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, F 1956-1992 (Box 3)
- Forum Club 1988-1993 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, G 1956-1992 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, H 1956-1992, 3 folders (Box 4)
- Correspondence, I 1956-1992 (Box 4)
- Correspondence, J 1936-1992 (Box 4)
- The Jefferson Scandals- Correspondence with Madison Books 1989-1992 (Box 4)
- The Jefferson Scandals- Fan Mail 1990-1992 (Box 4)
- The Jefferson Scandals- Finances 1989-1991 (Box 4)
- The Jefferson Scandals- Publicity 1991-1992 (Box 4)
- The Jefferson Scandals- Reviews 1991-1992 (Box 4)
- Correspondence, K-Ke 1956-1992 (Box 4)
- Correspondence, Kf-Kz 1956-1992 (Box 5)
- Correspondence, L 1956-1992 (Box 5)
- The Last Review- Correspondence with Editor Louis D. Rubin 1982-1985 (Box 5)
- The Last Review- Fan Mail 1982-1986 (Box 5)
- The Last Review- Finances 1982-1990 (Box 5)
- The Last Review- Publicity 1984 (Box 5)
- The Last Review- Reviews 1984-1985 (Box 5)
- Correspondence, M-Me 1956-1993, 3 folders (Box 5)
- Correspondence, Mf-Mz 1956-1992, 2 folders (Box 6)
- Mr. Jefferson's University- Publicity 1988 (Box 6)
- Correspondence, N 1956-1992 (Box 6)
- New Virginia Review- Board Correspondence 1982-1989 (Box 6)
- New Virginia Review- Personal Correspondence 1982-1990 (Box 6)
- Correspondence, O 1956-1992 (Box 6)
- P - Correspondence 1956-1993, 2 folders (Box 6)
- Pistols and Pointed Pens- Fan Mail 1987-1992 (Box 7)
- Pistols and Pointed Pens- Finances 1987-1992 (Box 7)
- Pistols and Pointed Pens- Publicity 1987-1988 (Box 7)
- Pistols and Pointed Pens- Reviews 1987-1989 (Box 7)
- Lewis Powell, Jr. - Correspondence 1971-1994 (Box 7)
- Correspondence, Q-R 1956-1993, 3 folders (Box 7)
- Richmond(paperback) - Correspondence with the University Press of Virginia 1990-1991 (Box 7)
- Richmond(paperback) - Fan Mail 1991 (Box 7)
- Richmond(paperback) - Finances 1991 (Box 7)
- Richmond(paperback) - Publicity 1990-1991 (Box 7)
- Richmond(paperback) - Reviews 1990-1991 (Box 7)
- Correspondence, S 1956-1992, 2 folders (Box 7)
- Society of the Cincinnati 1973-1987 (Box 8)
- Southern Academy of Letters, Arts, and Sciences 1978-1986 (Box 8)
- Branch Spalding - Correspondence 1969-1981 (Box 8)
- Speeches 1958-1988 (Box 8)
- Speeches - Invitations 1978-1988 (Box 8)
- Speeches - Notes and Clippings 1961-1985 (Box 8)
- Supper Club 1969-1981 (Box 8)
- Correspondence, T 1956-1993 (Box 8)
- Thanksgiving 1965-1986 (Box 8)
- Correspondence, U-V 1969-1992 (Box 8)
- United States Historical Society - Articles and Correspondence (2 folders) 1969-1993 (Box 9)
- United States Historical Society - Miscellaneous 1969-1993 (Box 9)
- University of Virginia Alumni - History 1982-1990 (Box 9)
- University of Virginia Library - Gifts of the Virginius Dabney Papers 1969-1992 (Box 9)
- University of Virginia Library - Permissions to Use the Virginius Dabney Papers 1965-1982 (Box 9)
- University Press of Virginia - Correspondence 1973-1992 (Box 9)
- University Press of Virginia - Finances 1983-1992 (Box 9)
- Virginia Center for the Creative Arts 1980-1982 (Box 9)
- Virginia Commonwealth University - Distinguished Professorship 1988-1990 (Box 9)
- Virginia Commonwealth University History- Correspondence with Ed Ackell 1983-1991 (Box 10)
- Virginia Commonwealth University History- Fan Mail 1987-1988 (Box 10)
- Virginia Commonwealth University History- Publicity 1987-1988 (Box 10)
- Virginia Commonwealth University History- Reviews 1987-1989 (Box 10)
- Virginia Commonwealth University History- University Press of Virginia 1983-1988 (Box 10)
- Virginius Dabney's Virginia- Fan Mail 1986-1987 (Box 10)
- Virginius Dabney's Virginia- Finances 1986-1992 (Box 10)
- Virginius Dabney's Virginia- Publicity 1986-1987 (Box 10)
- Virginius Dabney's Virginia- Reviews 1986-1987 (Box 10)
- Correspondence, W 1956-1993, 3 folders (Box 10)
- Correspondence, X-Z 1969-1992 (Box 10)